all right welcome everyone to cohort 4
of the textbook group
it's June 6 2023.
so
appreciate hearing everyone's
introductions
in that first section I'm going to share
the screen and we'll look at the coda
which is our shared workspace and has
all the information and it's also a work
in progress and one that you can edit or
comment so
please feel free to raise your hand
whenever you have a thought or a
question
and also you can write into the chat in
Zoom
and in this first meeting we're gonna
like go over a lot of the sections of
the coda and also just like take
questions and have discussions on
how the textbook group will proceed
so
the uh top page on the coda is on the
top left
just to give a little bit of some
overview of Coda overall you can hide
the sidebar if you want to focus on a
page you can also collapse the nesting
of pages
when you're within a page
um some pages are not editable like just
just because they're kind of static
content
but you'll find that editing on editable
pages is is roughly like any other kind
of online text editor
and we're gonna go through the sections
and see more about what they all do and
how they come into play and so on so
the top page give some information on
the active inference Institute and on
the textbook group overall and then also
there's the textbook itself which can be
just right clicked and downloaded
so it's an open source textbook which is
really awesome it came out about one
year ago in 2022 so it's early days for
this first version of the first textbook
of active inference
and uh
we also can have a lot to do to fill in
the dots and add questions and contacts
extra resources
it's uh quite a work to have made a
pocket-sized book
that covers active inference but you'll
also find that in these discussions
especially as people look towards the
applications and philosophy and so on
that we bring in a lot of other
resources and questions so it's not like
strictly just the textbook but that's
our attractor
directory gives and also an encoder you
may want to switch between light and
dark on the top right if you wanted to
to look different on your computer
uh directory provides just a few
sections of this coda
and what they're for
live meetings
uh here in cohort four probably be most
uh interested in cohort for itself
so just as a kind of like who we are or
where we're at I yesterday brought in a
few different visualizations
um just anecdotally we heard in the
introductions people's backgrounds
different like um uh educational larval
stages
but this graphic
is just a snapshot of the forms
when people have registered so this is
across cohorts just to get a better
sampling
um the x-axis is self-assessed
familiarity with octave inference
not familiar with zero highly familiar
100 and then Computer Science Biology
and maths familiarity in green blue and
red and uh it's awesome to see that
there's basically a
painting of the canvas so that's the fun
we have people with a lot of different
backgrounds and as we leave this
interdisciplinary conversation where
there's going to be math and analytical
equations coming into play there's going
to be computer science and pseudo code
and computational architectures coming
into play there's going to be biology
and mammalian neurophysiology coming to
play and also all these other domains
that people mentioned like clinical
setting Logistics and supply chain music
perception Etc like those even more you
know there could be more colors but
this is also to say like
everyone's Journeys and backgrounds are
really welcome it's not that everyone is
highly familiar with any of these topics
we're all learning these topics and even
those who have more familiarity
hopefully slash actually want to teach
and and share it
so we want to just highlight the
accessibility and also the rigor and the
applicability of all of this coming
together
and then also um
also self-described people's synchronous
and asynchronous time commitment
on a relative Spectrum so it's not even
with time units but uh synchronous
contributions as we'll look more at in a
few minutes
are like coming to this weekly
synchronous discussion
so those are always great to join and
asynchronously we'll look more at the
practices later
but that includes
your own reading and annotating and
working with the textbook and also
there's a lot of ways to do asynchronous
contributions
in this Coda that leverage so that other
people can also benefit from your works
in terms of the cohort for live meetings
themselves
um
also control and plus or minus or
control and scroll you can change the
size on coda
um top link is a calendar link for all
the textbook group meetings so get into
your own time zone
this playlist
is going to have there's no videos in it
yet but it's going to have all of the
videos for cohort for so for comparison
like um here's the playlist of cohort
three
so the welcome meeting going on through
that was the first half that they
completed in cohort three so that will
also uh be there
uh questions we'll talk about soon
and then the playlist with background
and context video for each chapter
um Ali and I did this live stream about
two weeks ago
and we clipped it into the uh
constituent parts
and this is something that we have
introduced for this cohort and it wasn't
there in previous cohorts they are about
20 minute videos
that just kind of scroll through the
chapter
and just talk about the structure of the
chapter and just broadly what's in it
and the idea is these videos are there
for you before we have the discussion on
that chapter so it can just be a useful
supplement to your
learning or preparation
um
our meetings are weekly and they
alternate between 13 and 22 UTC so some
people may be able to join both of these
times or just one or neither
um the video recording is going to be in
this link column to the right in just a
few hours following each meeting so you
can always review
um
we're in the onboarding and overview and
next week will be pretty similar like
also we'll have unrecorded introductions
for a different set of people who will
be there
um and then we'll go over the code again
so that video in some ways will be
slightly overlapping with this one
and then going forward we do two weeks
per chapter so between now and the end
of August we're going to cover the first
five chapters of the book which is like
part one the kind of epistemic section
of the book
and
during that two-week period it flies by
there's a lot to learn a lot of areas to
go into
so we're gonna basically
welcome you to join every uh cohort for
live meeting or the same time slot if
you want to join cohort threes
uh discussions
which are like on chapter six through
ten
at alternating times but there's there's
no reason not to join it's all part of
the same book and you may just also see
other things by looking later into the
book too
um
okay continuing on and again just write
any question in the chat or raise your
hand if you would like to
um get a little bit more details or ask
anyone who's previously participated in
the groups
um so onboarding just gives a few other
pieces of information of course it's all
it's all welcome to do it how you want
to do it
um there's some rules and guidelines
about this open science space
in terms of what and how we share
um being under Creative Commons and and
just
being
pro-social learners
in this textbook group
for student practices
um also
total work in in
uh progress
what do we really do when we're learning
active inference
here are some of them some practices
and also what that practice looks like
and what work products it results in
and these include everything from
um short little notes that you write to
yourself or updates in your own personal
knowledge system
to writing blog posts or adding
contributions directly to this Coda
which then can be leveraged because
everyone's working in this same space
um also just
organizing your information environment
taking a break teaching others building
physical models
working on projects like there's many
ways that we can engage in in these
um materials
and then there's also just some other
pages and templates that you might find
useful you can also make your own coded
document if you want to play around with
some of these templates
um
so that's kind of the the overview on
the textbook group we're going to be
working two weeks per chapter
hangout connecting asking a lot of
questions and now let's go into a lot of
these sections that have a lot more
content
um so
again you can download the PDF of the
textbook itself however increasingly we
have a lot of the materials of the
textbook in the coda so that they can be
really easily referenced and we'll see
what that looks like
so
um just
going through
um equations
most of the chapters have equations
and it's an ongoing project to connect
the equations for example equation 2.6
unexpected free energy it's like we're
going to get there
but even with a lot of familiarity and
math one might not know exactly how each
variable is being used here and so it
ends up being a friction for learning an
application
and so what we can do is we can develop
natural language representations of
these equations
2.5 is completed
um that use the active inference
ontology so everywhere you see like an
at in a blue
is uh calling a row in Coda and so for
example at
surprisal
and so then by mousing over
you can see where it exists what kinds
of definitions are there for that term
so observation here's a proposed
definition and this is developed as part
of the active inference ontology
um which is another project at The
Institute and more generally having this
equation in a table
allows us to connect it with the latex
code it allows us to also call this Row
in the coda like figure two four Mouse
over
oh
okay figure two four so it it helps be
really clear with where we're
referencing a certain like figure or
equation
um
figures also there's the figure in each
of these rows of this table and so that
allows us to call different figures
and to to um have discussion around the
figure
so here's just like oh figure 1.2 like
this is going to be also a kind of core
figure this is the low road and the high
road to active inference which is going
to be chapter 2 and chapter three
and then there's discussions that we can
have
about those topics so kind of in general
adding anything somewhere
is going to be better than adding
nothing nowhere
so just add first and we can always
reorganize later if needed
in general though adding directly to
wherever there's already notes in
discussion
or
um just
however you see fit it's it's great to
increment that way
um continue on with these kind of like
uh equations and figures before we get
to the the textbook chapters itself we
have the uh boxes in the table
so box 2.1
so just screenshots of all the boxes
and then um code we have a code repo um
Ali and and others I hope that we can
share more about other uh ongoing
resources and then also for people who
are interested to
the the code implementations
here are um many dozens in different
languages
of different uh packages and
implementations of active inference
models
so
we can return to the use later okay so
on to the um chapters themselves
um
here are the 10 chapters and the three
appendices of the book
and also a detailed table of contents
here's what happens in each of the
chapters so for example in um two weeks
from now when we get into chapter one
what is that going to be like
so in chapter one
uh one other useful tip in code is you
can you can always click on somebody's
little token on the top
um of the document and go to where they
are in the document
so if you just click on the pie you'll
be able to like follow where um this
user is
so the top of the um chapter one page
first is just an embed of the YouTube
video
with um Ollie and I giving the 20 minute
overview
then
there are the chapter one questions
which we'll come back to there's 33
questions
and then there's just sort of broader
discussion on on this
so the question is kind of like
a minimal epistemic action
and so whether it's a beginner and it's
like
every question is either going to be
new to you at the very least
it may have been something that's
already addressed or addressable which
is totally perfect that's why we want to
connect you with that information
it could also be a new question that
might support other Learners maybe
coming from a similar Vector as you to
be accelerating their active learning it
might even be a novel question period
and a research Avenue so
adding questions is just like always the
right thing to do
um to add questions you can just go to
the bottom of the table and just add
rows with enter
and then just type your question
um so and you can also upvote questions
with the interesting
so for example
um con organisms minimizing surprise
introduced on Page Six
how are prior assumptions established
when the organism's new or in novel
environments and then this textbook
reference okay chapter one page six or
here figure 1.2 you can Mouse over again
see what it was
and then in the answers and discourse
it's a canvas that pops up and so here
we've explored this a little bit and
we've also talked about like if if we
get a minimum number of upvotes like if
we get like you know 15 up votes or
something maybe we could
um curate the answers into a short video
so now we have a three minute video on
like addressing this and have another
like link here just things that we can
Implement as we continue the cohorts
um but in the answers and discourses
this is like a huge opportunity for
um
adding resources adding um other
associations that you have adding
applications or why would this matter in
a domain
so again always cool to add to these
Pages or to to
re-structure it
however you see fit and just improve
this because we revisit these cohort
after cohort and people on their own
time are are looking through these
questions
time after time so if you think that
there's an improvement that you can make
to like this question
and the discourse that's like a huge
contribution
um when we meet for a given chapter
um we will we we
of course uh don't assume like total
understanding whatever that would mean
but in general
we're going to um come to the questions
and in the beginning of like a chapter
one discussion like in in two weeks from
today
first just anyone can give their overall
Reflections or comments or thoughts on
the chapter or their experience reading
it or what stuck with them
then we'll move to the questions and
we'll look to
um
the questions that were highly
upvoted already
or questions that are kind of pressing
in the moment
and then look to improve
our feeling on those questions
so hopefully that
um makes sense
um and people can and then uh
uh we'll see another kind of lens on the
questions coming up one important piece
here is that the textbook doesn't have
questions it doesn't have
self-assessments
um or uh you know
anything like that
so
over the
years we will see if this can actually
be something vital in enabling the
textbook to be part of like an
educational ecosystem
to enable it to actually be used in
courses and so on
by creating these um by sourcing and
curating these questions so a question
could be anything from just like
in figure x what are the three kinds of
this
it doesn't need to be like a super hot
take it can just be a very
straightforward question or it can be
like what might this mean I mean what's
the distance between mind and brain in
the context of free energy principle
it's not going to be a one sentence
answer necessarily there's always like
more to add more to associate there
um but in general when we come to
discuss a chapter we're going to like
just have any general comments and
thoughts on it
um and then look to the questions
and just have it like conversationally
so that's going to be the case for for
each chapter
like here there's already 45 questions
from previous
um
uh cohorts on on chapter two you know
low road so
um chapters one through five that's the
section that we're in in this interval
then chapter six or ten chapter six is
where you get to like the recipe for
active inference modeling
and so that is where you start building
a generative model and working through
that process but chapter one through
five have a lot of background
information
so those are the um textbook sections
then we have a kind of further discourse
so here's the
here's the um questions themselves so
you can always go to cohort four
questions that's our cohort and if you
just want to add like to a chapter two
or I'll just add one that's a chapter
one here
this will help us see like which
questions specifically came up in uh
chapter in uh in cohort four
so it'll just um automatically be tagged
with cohort for it doesn't it's not
really important like who initiates the
question per se because we're always
going to be modifying it and so on but
if you just want to have a place to see
just the cohort for questions you can
add to this table and they're all views
of the same table so it's all if it's in
chapter one here it's going to show up
on the chapter one view when we get to
that chapter as well
um so questions again are a huge way to
contribute whether just by seeding a
question or by addressing
and not just because
this is how we reduce our uncertainty
the imperative and active inference is
uncertainty reduction slash bounding not
simply reward maximization so it's a
massive way to contribute to
write to uncertainties are having so
seeing those uncertainties as like calls
to action instead of um reasons to like
disconnect from learning or to to not
contribute to this shared niche
um
over the uh seasons
we've had a fun math learning group
different cohorts have done this very
differently sometimes it's been like uh
in the Discord just kind of like a
different like an office hours
and the math learning Group which I I I
hope multiple um people will
re-engage with however
um
has explored various topics related to
on one hand the accessibility and
onboarding to the math
and on the other hand to a lot of the
rigor and derivations of the math so
it's done everything from from kind of
looking for just like a math based
overviews uh curating resources on some
of the background mathematics like
Matrix algebra or um stochastic calculus
different
backgrounds and math learning
we can explore notation
we have a lot of questions about math
learning
um like general questions about math and
about how what we see in the analytical
equations
are related to these broader
um philosophical questions or the domain
specific questions that we have
so
um and then also there's ideas and
insights and so here just if people want
to like it's not necessarily a question
but they just want to be like oh this is
just like this is an Insight I had from
like
then they can add it
[Music]
um
there are resources
so here
um Ali's provided a nice list of extra
Resources with a rough ranking by by
technical level
so for people who want to to see other
technical or non-technical resources on
octimf
uh other videos and books but a lot of
resources are also just shared in the
question where they're asked
um let's see future textbook groups so
here's feedback forms
um we'll update this so it has cohort
for but you can just always leave
feedback
um you can share also just plain text
notes with like these are things people
have brought up previously about future
textbook groups these are quite
extensive um notes
um Errata there's a few typos in the
book
and so that just small little comments
or just other thoughts people have
uh projects
projects are a table here where people
can write what their idea is for
applying active inference
and uh connect with other people who
might be interested in something similar
so these range from uh contributions
that improve the textbook groups
themselves
like doing math derivations
um recording the textbook as an
audiobook
um doing other kinds of enrichments and
background materials on the textbook to
just people who have uh different
cognitive functions or systems of
interest that they want to be applying
active inference towards but it's always
you can put little stub ideas and we can
just revisit it periodically and
especially towards the end of the
textbook group
um facilitate people working on these
projects but like you're in the right
place to literally learn the background
information
to facilitate these kinds of
collaborations
um last section
is active inference tables
so the active inference ontology you can
go to this website this is essentially
the language that we speak in active
inference to understand the core
ontology terms
and there aren't an open-ended number of
them
I mean in principle there are but in in
the present moment there's only about
64. to understand these core terms and
their relationships
and their their rationale is to be
fluent in active inference as a language
skill so many of these terms are
everyday terms accuracy action attention
agency agent ambiguity Behavior
there are a few terms that aren't
everyday terms like expected free energy
but regardless of your level of math
familiarity with that equation in
specific you'll be able to kind of see
where it fits in to the ontology
um and also translations are available
for many languages
if anyone has any other languages that
they'd like to add or they they see
Corrections that's useful because of
course the ontology is not um English
based
in principle but we bring the ontology
in
as a table
and that allows us to connect the
questions that we have or the
descriptions of equations
with the terms and the formal knowledge
structure so again like looking at
equation 2.5
this equation for variational free
energy
can be looked at as an equation or we
might want to hear it for an audiobook
or just for our own understanding about
the notation to see it written out
and then even further there's like notes
and and discourse that people can have
and derivations that can be provided so
that's like how how many ways that we
can go from just
this figure or this equation
to
integrating it more with what it means
to learn and use active inference
active inference research here's just uh
some of our uh preliminary Knowledge
Management type work based upon a uh
project with RJ and blue where we use
the ontology to then analyze the
literature
and assess like for example the change
in different uh term frequency through
time in the open source active inference
literature so these are the kinds of
projects we have at The Institute but
can help provide uh surveying or
analysis or Awareness on the literature
in a more structured way
um
and live streams so like uh from this
website you'll be able to see our
several hundred live streams but we
commonly reference these as the papers
that are discussed and the guests who
join are
we believe some of the most relevant
but if you are looking for other
materials this is like a good place to
look so
that is the overview of the textbook
group again
they're synchronous and asynchronous
ways you can participate it's all up to
you synchronously the times are listed
in the core4 live meetings table where
you can join at the same time weekly if
you want
you can re-watch the videos
you can do your own work and your own
practices
people are also encouraged to write
questions
to
um seed the discussions
and then when we come to chapter one
discussion in two weeks
we're going to look at the the
cohort four questions that have been
submitted
and start with those
um and then look if um those are gone
through to the other questions that have
been submitted
so we just take a active question-based
approach during these discussions
outside of this introductory
um
session they're broadly gonna be like
hearing people's thoughts and
Reflections and questions arising and
just looking to capture those questions
and and develop them
so
does anyone have any
thoughts or questions on this
yes Daniel I have a question
can you hear me yes yep yes um I was
trying to get into this Coda website
that you just showed us
um somehow
I couldn't get into it because it seems
that cohort IV
website is not up running is that the
reason
I'm going to put the link again into the
chat
okay what happens when you go to that
link
all right let me let me try
package yeah it is working great okay
great thank you thank you yeah thank you
so I should bookmark it yesterday so
that I can this is a good a good link to
bookmark yeah okay
so here's like from part one of cohort
three here's the video recordings
so it'll look just like that as we go
through
any other
just thoughts or questions
so yeah me again just one more question
so in terms of learning uh
style so we're going to read the
question first read the chapters first
right before the meeting during the
meeting it was odd about uh discussion
and answering and asking questions right
yes broadly yes like
um
one does not have to read the chapter or
or anything
if if they don't have any time of course
they do not have to that being said
we're going to discuss chapter one on
this day
so the way to prepare for that
discussion would be ideally to have read
the chapter again there's no complete
understanding but just like understand
what is in the chapter
maybe look at what the sections are
[Music]
um
then if there is more time then you can
engage in more uh practices
so whatever practices around chapter one
are aligned and relevant for you
you could plan about learning chapter
one you could set aside the time to
learn for chapter one read chapter one
write short notes or a Blog on chapter
one
talk with a friend connect with somebody
in the textbook group or just like uh
you know with your colleagues or your
friends
chapter one doesn't have equations but a
lot of the future Ones Will
you could look to the chapter one
discourse in the coda
and review that discourse and see what
other people have asked and then where
you see relevant
add more resources if somebody put you
know if there was two Resources with
examples and you know there's a third
one
just I have example and that's huge
um you can organize information so that
it becomes more accessible for you so
there's like less of an activation
energy barrier
to learning or to contributing however
you see
you can uh you know go on a a walk or
lift or something or meditate and think
about chapter one
you can start to work with the
computational
implementations the open source ones
that are all listed here or however you
see
so each of these practices or more that
people can suggest
we kind of turn our attention to this
chapter
for that interval
and we'll say oh and it's going to come
up in chapter four but here's the here's
how it's coming up in chapter one
so it's not like we're only in that one
range of pages but we try to like keep
that as our
center of attention
as we move through it
and then the best way to that could
happen would be if the people who show
up
have
done whatever preparation is relevance
okay thank you
maybe Ali
or anyone else if there's a thought or a
question or What's um what's another
something that would have been helpful
to have known
earlier in the textbook group
uh yeah just I wanted to mention
uh we're developing some supplementary
materials uh which uh I believe will
hopefully prove a helpful
um while studying chapters
um especially the early chapters and
particularly uh the most heavy chapter
and with the chapter four because uh
some of the mathematical details about
the derivations of the equations uh are
a kind of glossed over in the book so we
hope that those supplementary materials
will help to fill the Gap otherwise
I believe these discussions in the live
sessions uh can be really uh
helpful and Illuminating uh and uh
obviously
one of the main objectives of these
discussions is to clarify any
misunderstandings or even deepen our
insights into the matters of the
contents of the book even beyond
the specific contents of the book so
um yeah
yeah
I mean it's the fourth cohort so we've
done things some certain ways which you
can see in the previous recordings
also though it can always evolve so if
you see
um you want to try a different language
office hour
um or you want to have a special session
for just like math learning group
focusing on the fundamentals
um Bayesian equation Matrix algebra if
you want to work with Ali and and
Jonathan on some of the
uh derivation work
if you want to start to sketch out cases
in a given domain
like
we just want to hold those up as
practices as affordances opportunities
for action for you in this
group
communicate to others that those are
possible ways to learn and apply active
inference
foreign
thoughts or questions on this
who well
if you want to join next week at the
later time
you're welcome to it'll be
fairly similar to today
um you can also join at this same time
weekly where we'll be in cohort 3
working through chapter six through ten
hopefully in two weeks
from right now we'll come back to
chapter one and there'll be a bunch of
new questions
and then we're going to look to covert
for questions first
and and uh upload each other's questions
again highly upvoted questions we're
going to make short videos for and and
if somebody like wants to do that kind
of
project or or process we can we can
participate on that as well but yeah
we're just gonna like look to see what
questions people have raised and cohort
for
whether they can make it to the meeting
or not and if someone raises something
new in the meeting then we'll just add
it as a question
it'll all funnel into the chapter one
questions
so we can continue to improve the
discourse and again so that we all have
uncertainties when we're learning active
inference or any topic that is the
fundamental
and so when those questions arise we can
either Point towards where they've been
addressed
or their new questions which are special
on their own way
so
okay
if anyone has any other
comments in the last minute
all right
great in that case
yes thank you and uh see you in one or
two or whenever weeks
um
farewell everybody goodbye
you thank you Daniel thank you everyone